<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians garment A sermon preached in London, by the late faithfull minister of Gods word, Master Paul Bayne.</title>
            <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05990</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113830</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849059</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849059</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14190</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05990)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14190)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 697:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians garment A sermon preached in London, by the late faithfull minister of Gods word, Master Paul Bayne.</title>
                  <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. P[urslowe] for Ralph Rounthwaite, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Flower-de-luce and Crowne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14190:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14190:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIANS GARMENT.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached in <hi>London,</hi> by the late faithfull Miniſter of Gods Word, Maſter <hi>Paul Bayne.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GAL. 3.27.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>All that are baptized into Chriſt, haue put on Chriſt.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>COL. 3.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When Chriſt which is our Life ſhall appeare, then ſhall yee alſo appeare with him in Glory.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. P.</hi> for <hi>Ralph Rounthwaite,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at the Signe of the <hi>Flower-de-luce</hi> and <hi>Crowne.</hi> 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14190:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14190:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader, I doe the rather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this following Sermon vnto thee: Firſt, becauſe I doe obſerue, that all the other workes of this holy man of GOD, vvhich haue beene committed to the Preſſe, ſince his death, are generally ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, and embraced of all the Godly; And ſecondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I hauing had other copies of his works in my hands, (as his firſt largeſt Letter of all, exciting to Repentance, and New obedience; and another Sermon of his, vvhich intreateth ſoundly, and in briefe manner, concerning the Apoſtaſie from true grace, which may be in Gods children, and from thoſe ſeeming temporary graces vvhich may be in the wicked) both vvhich are now printed; I thought good not to bury this other Sermon of his, which followeth, in darkneſse and obliuion. Thirdly and laſtly, I was the rather willing to commit the ſame to the publike view of all, in regard of the Author thereof, who was, and is ſtill reuerenced, and beloued of all the children of God, which euer knew him: eſpecially of all thoſe, which had any fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar acquaintance &amp; communion with him; who while he liued, was a bright Starre in the right hand of Chriſt;<note place="margin">Reu. 1.20.</note> who, as a cleere candle, ſhined ſo long vnto others, vpon the candleſticke where Chriſt had placed him, vntill by giuing light vnto others, hee had almoſt conſumed and
<pb facs="tcp:14190:3"/>ſpent himſelfe;<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.11.</note> who liued as a gentle Father, and a tender Nurſe among thoſe of the children of God vvhich hee had committed vnto his teaching; who was of the ſame minde with that holy Apoſtle, that hee would very gladly haue ſpent,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.15.</note> and been ſpent himſelfe for their ſoules, ouer which hee was appointed to watch; though the more abundantly he had loued them, the leſſe he ſhould haue been beloued of them: ſo affectionately deſirous was he of them, that hee was willing to haue imparted vnto them, not the Goſpell of God onely, but alſo his owne ſoule, becauſe they were deare vnto him,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.8. Act. 20.24.</note> who counted not his owne life deare vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſo that he might haue finiſhed his courſe with ioy, &amp; the miniſterie which he had receiued of the Lord Ieſus, to teſtifie the Goſpell of the grace of God: which hee laboured to performe in a good and acceptable manner vnto him: For as hee was allowed of God to be put in truſt with the Goſpell, euen ſo he ſpake, not as pleaſing men, but GOD, which tryed his heart;<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.4. &amp; 6.</note> neither at any time ſought hee the praiſe and glory of men, but of God alone. He was like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, for hee was both a burning and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning light,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.35.</note> burning in himſelfe, with the fire both of an holy and ardent zeale for Gods glory, and of a pure and feruent loue of the ſaluation of his brethren; and ſhining forth vnto others, by the light, both of his vncorrupt and ſound doctrine, and alſo of his vnblameable, and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. But behold, this bright Starre, this burning Lampe, this ſhining Light, was at length eclipſed, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and by death quite extinguiſhed; but his memoriall ſhall continue ſtill amongſt vs, and ſhall be bleſſed; his good name,<note place="margin">Prou. 22 1.</note> which is to be choſen aboue great riches, and to be valued aboue all precious treaſures, ſhall neuer die, but ſhall freſhly ſhine forth for euermore. Seeing hee
<pb facs="tcp:14190:3"/>was ſo good a man, his loſſe is the more to be lamented of Gods Church, and children: being taken away, as for the vnthankefulneſſe of this wretched and wicked world,<note place="margin">Eſay 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1.</note> which was not worthy of him; ſo alſo from the euill to come.</p>
            <p>Reade this, and all other of his workes with reuerence; remember the things contained in them with diligence; and practiſe all the good duties therein vrged vpon thy ſoule with conſtancy: and if thou receiue any benefite, and comfort thereby, forget not to giue God the praiſe and glory which is due vnto him for the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> G. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:14190:4"/>
            <head>Maſter <hi>Bayne</hi> his Prayer before his Sermons.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR gracious God and mercifull Father in Chriſt: We confeſſe, that as wee are vnworthy to appeare in thy ſight, ſo wee are of our ſelues inſufficient to euery good worke; and much more to thoſe of ſpeaking and hearing thy Word: for which, who are ſufficient? Wee beſeech thee therefore, in the entrance of theſe our duties, to help vs with thy good Spirit, that the thoughts of our hearts, and words of our mouthes may be acceptable before thee. Wee confeſſe to thy glory and our ſhame, that we are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſinners: if we looke to our ſelues, as lying in the loynes of our firſt parents, we are a tainted ſeed, iuſtly diſinherited of glory: if wee conſider our ſelues, as comming into this light, we are all concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and brought forth in ſinne, which like a Leproſy hath ſpred it ſelfe into all the powers of vs; that what we haue done of our owne ſtrength, is abomination, and whatſoeuer is truely good, we haue altogether neglected it, there being not one that doth good, no not one. More particularly we acknowledge, euen we, to whom thou haſt beene mercifull, to make vs taſte how good thou art in Chriſt; that ſince the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall working of grace in vs, wee haue not ceaſed, through the relickes of our corruption, to multiply treſpaſſes againſt all thy commandements, eſpecially we haue prouoked the eyes of thy glory by taking thy Name in vaine, by comming to heare and ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:14190:4"/>thy Word without renewing our faith, and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; and ſo haue deſerued, that thou ſhouldeſt turne thy Ordinances to become a ſauour of death vnto vs: Yea, if in none of theſe kinds we had offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded heretofore, yet ſince we haue bowed our knees, making theſe our confeſſions, wee diſcerne ſuch blindeneſſe of minde, and hardneſſe of heart with vs in the ſame, for which thou mighteſt iuſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs, wouldſt thou deale in Iuſtice, and deny vs Mercy: Neuertheleſſe, ſeeing it pleaſed thee by faith in Chriſt to make vs thy ſonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, wee do in this regard enter thy preſence with boldneſſe, as it becommeth thy children, beſeeching thee to make vs able alwaies to challenge our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe before thee, that we may ſay with good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, making requeſts in the death and reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt: It is Chriſt, that is dead, yea who is riſen from the dead, who is at the right hand of God, and maketh interceſſion for vs. Who ſhall condemne vs, or lay any thing to the charge of vs thy choſen? To this end, ſend the holy Spirit of thy Sonne into our hearts, which may renew vs more and more to that heauenly Image from whence wee are fallen, which ſtandeth in ſauing knowledge, righteouſneſſe, and true holineſſe. And becauſe thou haſt appointed thy Word preached, for a meanes of begetting and ſtrengthening this faith, and perfecting thine owne Image in vs, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, bleſſe thy Ordinance at this time vnto vs; Thou, who haſt made the Miniſtery of it, a Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Spirit, in which thy Spirit worketh our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations: And becauſe we know, that when we ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:14190:5"/>receiue the greateſt benefite from thee, that then Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than is moſt malicious againſt vs; we beſeech thee to ſaue vs from the power of all ſpirituall wickedneſſe, and from the darkeneſſe, deadneſſe, wandring and wearineſſe of our owne hearts. O thou who haſt promiſed, that if we reſiſt Sathan, he ſhall flye from vs; grant, that we flying to thee in prayer of faith, may begin, proceed in, and conclude theſe, and all ſuch duties to the glory of thy name, and the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our true happineſſe. Bleſſe our dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne the Kings Maieſty, bleſſe his Perſon and his Throne, ſanctifie his heart, enlarge it euery day more and more for thy glory, his owne comfort, and the good of his people. Bleſſe the Queene, the Prince, with the Nobility and Clergie of this Land: giue them all, O Lord, from the higheſt to the loweſt, ſuch a meaſure of thy grace, that they may faithfully and conſcionably, according to their ſeuerall Callings, diſcharge ſuch duties both in Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as thou in thy ſacred Word haſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Wee beſeech thee to heare vs in theſe, and all things thou knoweſt needfull for vs: yea make vs to ſee that thou heareſt vs (for ſuch is our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion toward thee in CHRIST) that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we aske agreeable to thy will in his Name, it is giuen vnto vs, but make vs finde it by good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that our faith may be ſtrengthened, and that wee may teach all fleſh to reſort vnto thee, who art a God hearing prayer: To whom with thy Chriſt, and the Spirit, be giuen from our hearts all Honour, for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14190:5"/>
            <head>The Chriſtians Garment.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 13.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But put yee on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and take no thought for the fleſh to fulfill the luſts of it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtle hauing exhorted to the works of loue, doth in the 11. Verſe inforce this exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from a double reaſon. 1. The one taken from the neereneſſe of their reward, which made their diligence now more ſeaſonable. 2. The other from their preſent condition, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not in the night of ignorance, and luſt of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but liued in the day-light of knowledge and grace, which the <hi>Sun of righteouſneſſe</hi> ariſing in their hearts had brought forth: Such, who are now nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer the fruit, and end of their faith and loue, ſuch muſt be more diligent in the workes of them: for the end of euery thing is of ſuch force, that the neerer wee come to it, we do with more courage and diligence ply the meanes which do bring vnto it.</p>
            <p>Againe, though men in the night take reſt, and ſleep vnapparelled, not paſſing for vncomelineſſe; yet in the day they go out to labour, and haue care of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14190:6"/>ciuill decency: from which the Apoſtle doth propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably argue, that ſuch <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> whoſe night is paſt, who liue in the peep and break of the day, muſt ſettle themſelues, as is beſeeming for the day: this is mentioned in the 12. <hi>Verſe,</hi> and this that follows: And it is firſt more generally propounded in the 12. <hi>Verſe;</hi> 2. Repeated and further expounded in the 13. and 14. <hi>Verſes.</hi> The firſt hath two branches: 1. <hi>viz.</hi> Of caſting away that which was vnbeſeeming: <hi>Let vs caſt away the workes of darkeneſſe.</hi> The ſecond, of putting on ſuch an habit, as ſuted with the day, to which part there is a iuſt correſpondency in the amplification: for <hi>Verſe</hi> the 13 particularly vnfoldeth the works of darkeneſſe which we muſt auoide, and the 14. openeth the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite, which will well agree with vs, whoſe day is at hand: <hi>Put on Chriſt, and take, &amp;c.</hi> In which verſe is contained a double duty: The one principall: The other ſecondary, following vpon the former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable: the firſt, <hi>Put on Chriſt:</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Take no care for the fleſh, as concerning luſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the opening of which words wee muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the firſt member is laid downe by <hi>Phraſe</hi> of ſpeech borrowed from apparell, and putting on of it: ſo that not we, but Hee is euery where ſeene to liue in vs: this is reſembled by the action of <hi>putting on,</hi> which doth ſo couer the body, that not the body, but the rayment onely is diſcernable. Secondly, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who doth determine this action, is brought in, bearing the ſemblance of a garment, becauſe as that doth couer nakedneſſe, defend from the iniury of the aire, procure comelineſſe to the body before men: the like doth <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the whole man in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14190:6"/>ſight of God. The latter duty may be conceiued. firſt, as ſet downe indefinitely, <hi>Take no care for the fleſh.</hi> Secondly, as conſtrued by limitation, <hi>viz.</hi> ſo farre forth, <hi>as the fleſh luſteth againſt the Spirit in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To open which words three things muſt be vnfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: firſt, what is meant by <hi>Taking care:</hi> ſecondly, by <hi>Fleſh:</hi> thirdly, what <hi>Luſts</hi> are heere excluded.</p>
            <p>The firſt is a word which doth ſignifie prouidence and fore-thought, how to bring about this, or that.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The fleſh doth heere note forth the outward man: 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. For were it put for corruption of our nature oppoſite to the Spirit, the limitation follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz.</hi> as concerning <hi>Luſts,</hi> would ſeeme imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent: for corruption abſolutely, both roote and fruite is to be abhorred.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third thing is thus cleered, there are <hi>luſts</hi> naturall, and ſinfull; theſe are heere debarred.</p>
            <p>The ſumme is: grow vp ſo into <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Sauiour</hi> and <hi>Lord,</hi> that he may couer you ſo, that euery where not you, but he may be ſeene to liue in you; and though you cannot in this body liue without ſinne, yet be not harbingers and purueyors, making proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to fulfill ſinne: and though you cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome care of this outward man, giue no reſpect to the inordinate and ſinfull deſires of it.</p>
            <p>We ſee then firſt, what muſt be the daily indeuour of vs, to attire our ſelues euery where with <hi>Chriſt:</hi> I will not ſeek to proue this, which the Text holdeth forth ſo manifeſtly, but will leade you into a fuller vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of this duety by vnfolding theſe two points: Firſt, how we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as he is to be put on by vs. Secondly, how we come to put him on.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:14190:7"/>
            <p> Chriſt, as he is to be put on by vs, or of vs, muſt be conceiued: firſt, as a iuſtifier of vs from ſinne: ſecondly, as a ſanctifier, who doth free vs from the power of ſinne, rinſing away, by the water of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that ſtaine of corruption defiling our natures. Thirdly, as an example of life ſet forth for our imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>Learne of mee: for I am lowly.</hi> And ſo be you followers of me, ſo far forth as I follow <hi>Chriſt:</hi> for ſo farre forth as <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath reference to this effect of not caring for ſinfull luſts, ſo farre this conſideration may be fitly extended: yea ſo far, as he doth make vs and our waies beſeeme the <hi>Light,</hi> into which wee are tranſlated: but <hi>Chriſt</hi> both as an Authour and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne concurreth to this ſecondary duty of not taking thought for fulfilling the <hi>luſts of the fleſh:</hi> 1. As an Authour in iuſtifying vs, and ſanctifying vs: For ſin entred before guit: but guilt muſt be taken away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſinne can be aboliſhed, therefore hee iuſtifieth vs from guilt, then purgeth out our corruption. 2. As an Example, in that hee hath left vs a <hi>Preſident</hi> this way.</p>
            <p>This putting on of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is properly ſo called, or by a borrowed ſpeech, the proper putting on of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is, when we do by an affianced knowledge, and by conſequent affections come more and more to be vnited with Chriſt. As men are eſtranged from Chriſt by ignorance, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. ſo by knowledge (ſuch as is in truth and affectiue) they come to haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction with him: by faith hee dwelleth in our hearts, and we in him. This affiance and truſt to him is ſuch, that knowledge by benefit heereof doth vnite vs; otherwiſe he being in heauen, and ſeeing the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14190:7"/>glory of God euidently, would not make vs one with him, no more then a ſore eye is accorded with light being brought into it: yea affections increaſe this vnion; by loue our hearts cleaue to him, by hope, ioy, high eſtimation of him; whom though we haue not ſeene, yet we loue, and beleeuing, reioyce in him with ioy vnſpeakable, and glorious: <hi>I count all things droſſe in compariſon of the knowledge of Chriſt: Chriſt</hi> is ſaid to be our hope, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But ſome will ſay haply, Doth any thing but <hi>faith</hi> put on, and vnite vs with <hi>Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The firſt and radicall vnion, on which all fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing haue dependency, is made by faith onely: this layeth hold on God in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as now become our mercifull God, whoſe anger before threatned vs for ſinne; nothing beginneth, nothing continueth this <hi>Vnion,</hi> but faith: There is a ſecondary <hi>Vnion,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſoule cleaueth more and more vnto God, now reconciled vnto it; and this is done by meanes of the affections abouenamed, and the like, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now this preſuppoſeth the former: for were it not for this precedent <hi>vnion of faith,</hi> we ſhould flye from God as a conſuming fire, yea though we knew him, and that he is a gracious God in himſelfe, yet with thoſe vnbeleeuing ſpirits we ſhould tremble.</p>
            <p>Now we are ſaid to put on <hi>Chriſt</hi> improperly, by imitation, as a man is ſaid to put on the perſon of ſuch an one, whom in his geſture and otherwiſe hee repreſenteth. And thus when we do by knowledge, &amp; faith, &amp; holy affections, &amp; godly imitation, ſo grow vp into <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that he couereth vs; His Spirit from him worketh al our works in vs, &amp; for vs: <hi>Not we liue,</hi> but <hi>he
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14190:8"/>in vs, Gal.</hi> 1. that our inward and outward man are in ſome good meaſure conformed to that perfect pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, which he hath left vs in himſelfe to follow. Then we practiſe this duty heere enioyned, when this I ſay is truely endeuoured, which doctrine thus opened rebuketh many.</p>
            <p>There are not a few, which liue in groſſe ignorance of Chriſt his Perſon, Offices, and Conuerſation: How few are they, that labour for that confidence in his promiſes, which might ſettle their hearts quietly through his grace! But who almoſt of beleeuers doe tye Chriſt more neerely to them, by working their affections towards him, labouring to feele him their loue, hope, ioy? the want whereof maketh <hi>Chriſtians</hi> faith ſo weake, that when the winde and ſtorme of temptation ouertake them, they thinke <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them. For though theſe affections come from faith, yet they are daughters, which ſtrengthen their mother when ſhe is aſſailed.</p>
            <p>The wofull practice of <hi>Papiſts</hi> is hence diſcouered: for they faile in the thing to put on, and in putting it on: <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone they put not on: their faith is on my <hi>Lady, S. Peter, S. Paul,</hi> on their owne righteouſnes, workes, penall ſatiſfactions, Popes Pardons, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> I, but they hold <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As one hauing his hand full of this, or that, cannot catch hold of a third thing, but hee loſeth that hold he had of the former: So heere ſeeking ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in <hi>Saints,</hi> and themſelues, and the Churches Treaſury, they fall from <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Now, for their <hi>Faith,</hi> it is a bare knowledge, without confidence that hee loued them, and gaue himſelfe for them. Faith is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14190:8"/>preſumption, ſay they. Their faith maketh them like to ſuch, who carry garments vnder their armes, but leaue them to others to put on: ſo they content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to know, that the Sonne of God tooke our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, died to redeeme his Church, but that he is their Sauiour, and they his people, that hee loued them, and gaue himſelfe for them: this, which applyeth him, they diſclaime as preſumption.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, let vs prouoke our ſelues to ſeek this wel-beſeeming and ſweet-ſmelling garment, to be cloathed with this glorious Sunne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. It is the folly and madneſſe of men, that this rayment is no more in requeſt. Why are not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants aſhamed of their naked parts? They haue not vſe of reaſon ſo farre. Why are not mad men? Their reaſon is ſo depraued and peruerted, they think there is no ſhame in it: So heere our ſpirituall chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhneſſe, or madneſſe maketh vs not reſpect our ſpirituall nakedneſſe, ſo farre as to renew our care of putting on <hi>Chriſt</hi> daily.</p>
            <p>Many in adorning the body are exceſſiue, it is a yeere before they can haue done in dreſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and halfe the care of men is about the backe, but they haue not wiſedome once to thinke of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their ſoules araied with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his image.</p>
            <p>But let vs not deceiue our ſelues; glory is but an vpper garment: if we be found naked of this cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, we ſhall neuer be ouer-ſhadowed with that glory: Nay, Chriſt ſhall ſay, <hi>Taeke that gueſt without a wedding garment, caſt him into vnquenchable fire.</hi> In putting on our apparell, we ſhould raiſe our ſelues to ſuch like meditation.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14190:9"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>And take not care.</hi> From the ſequell and connexion of theſe, one with the other: wee ſee, that the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining of Chriſt, and retaining of our luſts to ſerue them, ſtand not together: the putting on of Chriſt, and putting off the willing ſeruice of theſe ſinfull luſts are inſeparable companions: you, that are <hi>Chriſts, haue crucified the fleſh, with the luſts of it: Gal.</hi> 5.24. <hi>Whoſoeuer is in Chriſt, is a new creature,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. If you haue learned Chriſt, as the truth is in him, you haue ſo learned him, as to put off the old man: <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. for the putting on of Chriſt doth tranſforme vs into his image, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. As the Aire darke in it ſelfe, ouerſpred with the light of the Sunne, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth inlightned.</p>
            <p>Againe, we ſee, that further then old apparell is put off, new cannot be put on. Beſides that, other things can no longer occupy the heart, whoſe affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are poſſeſſed, and filled with Chriſt: For looke as a woman, the more ſhe putteth on, and groweth vp into the loue of her huſband, the more ſhe grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out of luſting after any other: (the heart can true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue but one at once:) So we, our affections being once take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp with the loue of our heauenly Husband, do grow out of loue with adulterous deſires and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in the things of this world.</p>
            <p>If we well marke our ſelues, we may trace all our ſinnes to this beginning: <hi>viz.</hi> our not being cloathed with Chriſt. Were our hearts ſo true to him, as they ſhould be, we ſhould go ſafe, vndefiled by all the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements of this world; as a woman louing her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band loyally, is ſafe, though ſhe meete with ſollicitors to vnchaſtity.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:14190:9"/>
            <p> Which ſerueth to deiect the vaine preſumptions of many, who thinke that Chriſt is quickly learned ſufficiently, if they can the Creed, the Lords Prayer, haue Chriſtendome, be orderly Church-men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue at <hi>Eaſter;</hi> they think this is Chriſtianity enough: as for putting off of luſts, to which naturally their hearts encline, they thinke it needleſſe, and that God, who hath made, and knoweth our natures, doth not expect we ſhould be freed from that, which is by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in vs: But this is to get our leſſon by rote. Hee that crucifieth not his naturall ſinfull inclinations, hath no vnion nor communion with Chriſt: Yea, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe go together, ſuch muſt feare, who fauour themſelues in their luſts, when the deuill ſhall winde this dart againſt them: Such as are Chriſts, they cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie their luſts, but thou haſt ſpared, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to haue thine vntoucht. Well, it will make vs ſhake the head, they will be more bitter in their after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorrow, then euer they were pleaſant, while they were taſted.</p>
            <p>But if any weake ſoule ſhould thinke, becauſe they feele ſinne raging in them, and themſelues captiue to it, that therefore ſin is not mortified in them, they muſt know, that it is one thing not haue their ſinnes mortified, and another thing not to feele any ſtirring and mouing of it in them. It is ſaid truely then to be killed, when that is done vpon it, which will make it die in time, though it take on awhile: as a wound will ake and tingle after it is dreſſed with a healing plaiſter. Hee that feeleth it a burthen, wherewith he is vnwilling to be laden: He that deſireth to be ſet free from it: Hee that reneweth his faith toward
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14190:10"/>Chriſt, who is made of God his ſanctifier, and reſteth on him to ſee theſe workes of the deuill vtterly diſſolued, hee hath mortified his ſinne, though the deuil and ſinne ſhould neuer ſo vſurpe, and tyrannize in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> was crucified to the world, and yet he felt ſinne vſurping ouer him, and leading him captiue, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. The voluntary ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to it, mortification preſently cauſeth to ceaſe: the inuoluntary ſuffering of it, is ſucceſſiuely diminiſhed, but neuer till death totally remoued: wherefore in the ſecond place let vs reſiſt all luſts, as euer we will aſſure our ſelues, we are truely in Chriſt. What a ſhame is it for Chriſtians, not to haue power ouer their inordinate luſting in meates and drinkes, when a dog will be trained to ſtand vpon a Table, and touch nothing, which is not giuen him? How ſhall we thinke they perſwade themſelues truely that Chriſt hath ſhed his bloud for them, who cannot forbeare a ſuperfluous cup for his ſake, when their ſtomakes are before charged with more then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough? If a companion come in, though it were at their mouth, they would thence pull it and yeeld to him.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>Luſt</hi> is not ſatiſfied, when ſerued. What was <hi>Amnon</hi> the better when he had got his will of his ſiſter by violence? Nay, the very luſting for a thing maketh a good man, that he dare not touch it, when now it is preſent. When <hi>Dauid</hi> had a months minde to the water of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> hee would not touch it, when now it was bronght vnto him. What ioy could a good man take, who ſhould get <hi>Manna</hi> and <hi>Quailes</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:14190:10"/>with murmuring, and inordinate luſting? And thus in generall.</p>
            <p>More particularly, we muſt note, what is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of one in Chriſt: not to be a harbinger and purueyor, making prouiſion to fulfill his ſinfull luſts: ſin hath not willing obeyſance performed to it; You that are vnder grace, ſin raigneth not in you, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. But to conceiue of this the more fruitfully, we muſt open the difference betwixt the ſinning of one in Chriſt, and one that hath no true fellowſhip with him; which we may conſider: firſt, in their diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before ſinne: ſecondly, while they are in ſinning: thirdly, after ſin accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, before ſin, a true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> doth not plot and ſet downe with himſelfe aduiſedly in a ſinfull courſe; but he intendeth to walke vprightly before his God; ſin cloſeth with him beſides his purpoſe. <hi>The wicked ones in their beds deuiſe their miſchiefes. Micah</hi> 2.1. <hi>The godly are taken at vnawares, Gal.</hi> 6.1. Look as one trauailing in ſlippery waies, cannot but ſlide and fall ſometimes, yet he doth not purpoſely ſet himſelfe about it; ſo do the godly in their waies of ſinning. The wicked, who do it with full will, haue greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution and delight, while they are a working it, then the godly can haue. The Scripture ſaith, that <hi>the wicked hardneth his face, he will not be abaſhed in his courſe, but will go thorow:</hi> A Phraſe taken from a trauailer, who ſets his face againſt the ſtorme, and will on his way what weather ſoeuer commeth. Thus <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> thus that <hi>Ichoram</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who would, when two fifties were conſumed, ſend a third. Againe, ſinne is ſweet to them, as a looſing vnder
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14190:11"/>their tongues; for it is their meate and drinke to haue their wils; as it is a godly mans to do the will of his Father in heauen. Now thoſe, who haue a contrary ſpirit, cannot be ſo reſolute, and entire in following it, nor taſting any ſuch delight in it. I ſpeake compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiuely: For as they cannot ſo reſoluedly do the good they would, becauſe ſin luſteth againſt grace: ſo they are but halfe of them in ſin, becauſe the Spirit of grace luſteth againſt ſin in them. <hi>Dauid</hi> in his haſte would kill and ſlay; <hi>Abigails</hi> ſpeech charmeth him: when he had now committed ſinnes of infirmity, <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans</hi> ſpeech doth reclaime him. And doubtleſſe, the experience of all Gods children will confirme, that ſinne is but a bitter ſweet, while the Law of grace vp-braides them in doing it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, after that ſinne is attempted, if it be not executed, the wicked grieue, ſleep not, <hi>Pro.</hi> 4. For as a man faſting, for want of comfortable va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, ſuch as nouriſhment ſendeth vp to the braine, cannot ſleep: ſo theſe wanting that, which is as bread and meate to them, are kept waking through the vexation of it. But the godly defeated do at length, when the fit is a little off, at leaſt bleſſe God with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid: Bleſſed bee God, thy ſelfe, and thy counſell, that hath kept me from ſhedding of bloud.</hi> If it be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, the wicked, they make a ſport of it, are glad they haue their wils, paſſe from it impenitently. <hi>Eſau</hi> contemned his birthright, when he had prophanely ſold it. When <hi>Cain</hi> had done his murther, he ſaid, <hi>Am I my brothers keeper?</hi> Whereas the godly, their hearts ſmite them, they go forth and weep with <hi>Peter.</hi> For as meate vnwholeſome taken into a ſtomake, which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14190:11"/>hath ſtrength of nature, cauſeth either ſickneſſe or vomite: ſo where there is the life of grace, this poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſin once taken downe, cannot but make a ſicke ſoule.</p>
            <p>The vſe of which is to let vs ſee their fearefull eſtates, whoſe courſe is to plot reuenges, couetous reaches, to ſet meetings of good-fellowſhip, not letting men follow their Callings quietly; but prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them to ioyne in company: Such, who are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully bent: Such, as can brag, when they haue met with one in way of reuenge; can tell, with delight, oh, how merry they were! and repeat their vaine delights gladly; ſometimes their ſinfull villanies: That they haue laid vp ſuch a one. Such, as when they haue made a Conny of one in bargaining, can drink a pint vpon it: Such, as when they haue diſhonoured thoſe they ſhould obey, can brag, how they ſtood to them, and held them vp. Theſe wretches haue not, as it ſeemeth, any ſparke of grace, who can ſo well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coct their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this may comfort vs, who finde theſe ſignes in vs, that we haue fellowſhip with Chriſt: though ſinne dwell in vs, yet we do not purpoſely hold a courſe in it, wilfully and delightfully conuerſe in it, and go away with it remorceleſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> But one may heere obiect, that wicked ones do not continue, and fore-deſigne all the ſinnes they commit: Secondly, that they ſinne with relucta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and as <hi>Iudas</hi> had, haue their after-griefe: Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, againe: Godly ones ſometimes haue deepe fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches for bringing ſin about; as <hi>Dauid,</hi> in compaſſing, or couering his fault with <hi>Bathſheba.</hi> And the ſonnes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14190:12"/>of <hi>Iacob,</hi> What a ſtrange winde-laſe did they take to bring about their ſauage murther? It ſeemeth they may adde wilfulneſſe to their ſinning. Good <hi>Aſa,</hi> though God followed him with ſore ſickneſſe, yet would not ſeek to him, but to the Phyſicians. Yea, they may be vnrepentant after ſinne: For the ſonnes of <hi>Iacob</hi> did ſtoutly carry out their barbarous fact: <hi>Shall our ſiſter be made a whore? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt: for wicked ones, though they purpoſe not this, or that particular ſin: yet to follow their owne vnrenewed minde and will, they alwaies pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They ſinne with reluctation in groſſer crimes, ſuch as the world do note; but the righteous man in leſſer, ſuch as no man can challenge him for. The naturall man hath a reluctation betwixt the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of naturall light, and morall inclination of the will on the one ſide, and the enormous aberration of his ſenſuall wilfulneſſe on the other: But the godlies reſiſtance is betweene a new diuine quality in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will, and affections wrought by the Spirit of Chriſt, on the one ſide; and the remainders of our natiue corruption on the other: He hath after-griefe, but it is in ſuch crimes, as nature her ſelfe, leſſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, iudgeth reproachfull: Whereas the godly mans greefe is euen in good duties, that ſin will not let him do them, as he would. Againe, the naturall mans griefe is, becauſe of miſeries in Name, Bodie, or otherwiſe, which his offence hath bred to him: The godly man grieueth at the euill it ſelfe of ſinne, and at the offence of his God diſpleaſed with it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to the exceptions of Gods children, I
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14190:12"/>anſwer: Firſt, we ſpeake not of what Gods children do, when now they ſlide through infirmity, or are fallen into a ſpirituall ſickneſſe; but how it is with them, when they are themſelues through grace, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they are regenerated and new creatures. Secondly, I ſay there is a great difference: The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man doth thus, but not totally as the wicked. As it is with a ſick man, ſo it is with him, who is out of his naturall Conſtitution, ſo farre as the diſeaſe, or ſick cauſe hindreth and peruerteth the order of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: So the godly man hauing receiued the Diuine nature, doth not do thus according to his new being in Chriſt, but according as his ſtate is troubled by the ſicke relickes of ſin, which ſtill dwell in him. Againe, we muſt diſtinguiſh betwixt the generall courſe, and particular action, out of which ground the aboue-named particulars may be ſatiſfied: For they were done of them, now ſliding through weakeneſſe, or declining into ſickneſſe, as in <hi>Aſa:</hi> ſecondly, they were done not of their whole man, but of that ſick matter which did trouble their Conſtitution, and Diuine Nature they had receiued. Thirdly, theſe were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular acts, in compariſon of their generall courſe. <hi>Dauid</hi> now fallen into adultery, and downe vnder the fit of ſinne, did deſigne that murther; but he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by a wandring eye, without any premeditate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to offend; ſo the other in anger, though while the ſharpe fit ſtill continued, they could not but deuiſe a way of reuenge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſa's</hi> and <hi>Salomons</hi> were long ſickneſſes, into which they fell, preuented by frailty, beſides their purpoſe (I meane) their courſe in ſin they held in, which ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14190:13"/>farre forth as the fit, or working of lurking corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did actually get the better of Grace, they added wilfulneſſe to their courſe: but this was, when now they were by infirmity ouertaken, and fallen into ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſo far forth, as the mouing of ſicke matter, that is, of remaining corruption, got the vpper hand. The ſons of <hi>Iacob</hi> were impenitent, when they made that anſwer: for their choler was not yet cooled; wrath was ſtill vp, and godly wiſedome downe: But they were not ſo in ordinary courſe, nor when they were themſelues not tranſported with ſo violent paſſion: neither is it to be thought, but when their bloud was now cold, before the renewing of the Couenant, which preſently followeth, they did repent. As for <hi>Dauids</hi> fact, beſides that all aboue may bee applyed to it, he was abuſed by flattery; the right was doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, one affirming, another denying: Hee did, no doubt, though not directly in reuoking wholly that former grant, make <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> amends, ſo far forth as he grew ſecured of his innocencie.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing to be marked is, that hee, who put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on Chriſt, is not forbidden ſimply to care for the fleſh, but ſo farre forth as it luſteth inordinately.</p>
            <p>Concerning luſts; obſerue, that not care of the outward man, but onely then, when it ſinfully luſteth, is forbidden a Chriſtian man. <hi>No man hateth his own fleſh;</hi> That God, who commandeth vs not to kill, doth bid vs not to be wanting to our liues, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing ſuch things as ſerue for the iuſt comfort of them: Yea, a Chriſtian Charter is large this way; <hi>All things are pure vnto the pure:</hi> God hath created wine, as well as water; things of delight, as well as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14190:13"/>neceſſity; and the man of God, who ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary for ſobriety, is allowed a cup of wine for the benefit of his ſtomack, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.23. But when deſires grow beyond the bounds of Nature and Grace, they are not to be ſerued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> Heere it will be asked, how we know law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſires from ſinfull luſtings?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> By conſidering, 1. the obiect, 2. quality, and 3. quantity of them: If they be carried after things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, ſimply; as priuate reuenge forbidden, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, iniuſtice, &amp;c. Theſe are wicked, naught for ſubſtance, as we may ſay after a ſort. Thus when a womans minde ſtandeth to aſhes, lye, pitch, raw fleſh (as ſuch who do long, are ſubiect to theſe) we know them to be vnnaturall, becauſe they are after that, which is vnwholeſome, and agreeth not with nature, when ſhe is in her right frame and temper. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the quality of them, when they are vehement, though about a thing that is good: Vehement, I ſay, ſo that they worke a perturbation in vs, and put vs ſo off the hookes, that we are not our ſelues for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, theſe are ſinfull: <hi>Rachel</hi> might lawfully haue deſired children: but when it comes to <hi>Giue me chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or I die:</hi> To this, that ſhe will die of the ſullens, if ſhe haue them not, this lawfull deſire is depraued and become ſinfull. Thus wee know, naturall heate from vnnaturall: the naturall heate is ſo temperately diſperſed, that it diſturbeth not the ſweete content of natures Conſtitution; But theſe vnnaturall heats, they make the part glow to which they ſhoote, and breed a tedious diſtemper. So an ordinate deſire doth not interrupt the ſweete harmony of natures Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14190:14"/>but while it is kept in due order, a man walketh, not feeling diſturbance by it. Thirdly, the quantity: For if they be exceſſiue, and vnſatiable, they are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: To haue care of buſineſſe is lawfull; but when there is no end of it, one draweth on another; this is ſinfull: So, to take delight, is lawfull: but when men dwell vpon it, and vnſatiably after one, muſt haue a ſecond, after a ſecond, a third; this is groſſe ſenſuality: So to take a cup of wine is lawfull; but when one draught calleth on another, one meeting another; this is inordinate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> How doe wee know naturall thirſt from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The one is ſatiſfied with a draught or two: The other is ſo kindled by drinking, that it ſtill deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth drinke: as it fareth in Thirſts cauſed by Agues, Heates, and in Dropſy-like appetite by ſalt rhewmes prouoked.</p>
            <p>This then ſerueth firſt, to take away the ſlander of a <hi>Chriſtians</hi> eſtate, which heareth, as if it were bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all liberty; when indeed licentiouſneſſe onely, and ſinfull luſts are prohibited: ſtolne waters, ſinfull and intemperate abuſe, not the vſe of any creatures is reſtrained. True it is, wicked men thinke, there is no pleaſure, if they may not haue things after their owne minde: And as <hi>Daniel</hi> loued Pulſe better then the Kings diet, while he had it in holy order; ſo they contrarily thinke, that onely pleaſant, which is had in ſinfull faſhion: Neuertheleſſe it is not pleaſant, but onely ſeemeth ſo to their palates, diſtaſted with ſenſuality. Fennes are not the delightfulleſt places, becauſe Frogges like them; nor Thiſtles the beſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14190:14"/>meate, becauſe an Aſſes lippes deſire no better Lettice.</p>
            <p>Secondly, let vs bee aſhamed to runne into our luſts, becauſe God doth vſe vs ſo liberally, as to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold nothing from vs, that is good. If we allow out ſeruants plentifully that which is fit for them, wee take it the more heynouſly, if they paſſe their bounds, and take by ſtealth in hugger mugger: ſo may the Lord be highly offended with vs, ſeeing his hand is not ſtraight ouer vs. Let vs therefore ſhake off the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of ſinfull luſts, as euer we will haue aſſurance that we are Chriſts. A Luſt is an vnmercifull Tyrant, which will neuer be ſatiſfied, but taske thee more and more, the more thou obeyeſt it: And though men may thinke they ſhall loſe by this meanes, and part with pleaſure; the truth is, no man ever had loſſe by loſing a <hi>Courtezan:</hi> It ſhall bee thy gaine to breake off with theſe ſpirituall harlots. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
